>> Once upon a time, there
was a festival...
In Brooklyn.
A celebration of
American Black Dance.
There were choreographers
and dancers from the biggest
and the oldest companies
to the smallest and newest.
[ Music ]
From Harlem...
From Broadway...
[ Music ]
From dance theaters across
the country...
From the streets.
[ Applause ]
Come, join us.
Applaud the greats.
Replay the highs.
See what's new.
[ Applause ]
It's a great party.
It's not over yet.
[ Jazz Music/Clapping ]
[ Cheering ]
[ Percussion Music ]
>> Now, point, point,
point, point.
[ Woodwind and Percussion Music ]
>> And one, twist, twist,
front and stretch out.
And one, twist, twist,
[ Foreign Language Spoken ]
>> Side!
[ Inaudible ]
>> Back.
[ Percussion Music ]
Back.
I'm coming towards you.
[ Percussion Music ]
Back, back, back, back.
>> One.
[ Percussion Music ]
Faster.
[ Laughter ]
>> OK, OK, OK.
It was a shock.
Where is my arm?
What is my back?
Do I have legs?
I understand.
If you can dance,
you can dance.
>> Lookout Mick Jaggar.
I'm gonna start you up!
[ Traffic Sounds ]
>> Anybody got an extra ticket?
>> No.
>> Please have your
tickets ready.
Let me read 'em
and you weep.
>> Make sure it's tight because
once you start jumping up
[ Sharp Inhale ]
it's going to fall down.
[ Inaudible ]
>> Bring it up.
>> Bring what up? This thing?
>> Yeah.
>> We got to do this over.
[ Laughter ]
[ Excited scream ]
>> Get down Charlie Brown.
>> One, two, three, go.
[ Jumping rope ]
One, two, three, up.
>> Pick it up Wanda!
>> Three, three.
Four, four.
Five, five.
Six, six.
>> Exit, exit.
[ Laughter ]
>> Wanda, pick'em up Wanda!
>> Starting in four minutes
folks, please take you seats.
Ladies and gentlemen, we're
starting in four minutes.
Please take you seats.
>> We're going to break a leg.
We're going to break
twenty legs.
[ Background Music ]
>> Right side please.
To you left.
>> Thank you.
>> Please have your
tickets ready.
[ Background Conversations ]
[ Music ]
>> Growing up Cleveland,
I saw Asadata Dafora do the
Ostrich at Severance Hall.
It was the first time I
ever saw African dance.
Later I came to New York.
I studied with Katherine Dunham
and Charles Weidman,
but I never forgot
that first glimpse of Africa.
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Chuck Davis
>> Charles, I just--
>> Hi, Chuck.
Chuck, Let me, let me
give you some changes.
[ Music ]
>> As a choreographer in
America, I have the best
of both worlds, because I have
my traditional African heritage
with my contemporary
American training.
The Lenjen-go dance
and Mandiani
are two dance styles from the
Senegambia area of West Africa,
which are used in
a social context.
Lenjen-Go people will gather
every afternoon in the gambia,
late in the afternoons, and
they set about singing
and the drums, the
drums are going.
It's a perfect marriage
between music and movement.
[ Music ]
[ Music/Applause ]
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
>> I was very curious.
I loved anthropology and it
didn't take me long to know
that there was something
missing in the concert
and theatrical presentations
of American Black people,
that there was a whole
culture being overlooked.
>> When I danced with Katherine
Dunham, she was the best.
You couldn't go any higher and
when I danced her dance, "Shango"
I wasn't Charles Moore anymore.
I was possessed.
You have to be in
order to do the dance.
We were all a little afraid.
[ Suspenseful music ]
[ Crying out ]
[ Applause ]
[ Singing/Percussion Music ]
>> Hello.
[ Inaudible ]
This is Eleo Pomare.
>> Hi, how are you?
The thing that I try to reach
when I do "Junkie" is
articulated anger.
I'm not concerned about
"Junkie" as a junkie.
To me as a dancer, as a
performer, it's a study
in self-destruction and this
particular person chose drugs.
[ Jazz Music ]
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
>> Are you on now?
>> Whoops.
I started the Bucket Dance
Theater because I was in search
for a different dancer.
Most of my dancers, it
never even occurred to them
that they would be dancers,
professional dancers.
We have part-time jobs.
I have a full-time job.
I found some of them at parties.
I found some of them
on the basketball court
or the soccer field.
And I remember the first show
we did in Buffalo, New York,
when I was performing, they
were in the wings just watching
and that's when I knew
that they were turned on
and they understood what
it was all about finally.
I just had a fight in the
dressing room with them,
because someone had sent out to
get all this Kentucky chicken
to eat before the show
which dancers never do,
but they didn't know any better.
[ Background Applause ]
>> We've got to take places.
[ Music ]
"From Before" was looking back
at my origins in the West Indies
and seeing how I could
take away all the trimmings
and the costumes of
African or Caribbean dance
and strip it right
down to the bare bones.
[ Music: "The Path" by Ralph MacDonald ]
[ Singing, African Language ]
[ Applause ]
[ Percussion Music ]
[ Music/Applause ]
[ Singing, African Language ]
[ Applause ]
[ Singing/Applause ]
[ Singing, African Language ]
[ Applause ]
[ Percussion Music ]
[ Music/Applause ]
[ Carribean Music ]
[ Applause ]
[ Singing, African language ]
[ Jazz Fusion Music ]
[ Applause ]
[ Percussion Music ]
[ Funky Music ]
[ Synthesizer Music ]
[ Percussion Music ]
[ Singing, African language ]
[ Applause ]
>> It's all right now. We did it.
>> Oh, no I'm not
going to get dressed.
I'm too excited
to get dressed.
>> I know you're excited, but
just get out of the
men's dressing room please.
>> Okay.
>> But let me kiss you first.
>> Bucket made that mark.
>> Bucket made their mark.
>> Right.
>> History of BAM.
>> Anything's possible now.
The sky's the limit.
>> Alright, alright.
Yes. I'm going to have so
much by the time I get back.
>> Please take your seats
for the second half.
>> When they brought
their dancers to America,
the Africans brought
their glides and shuffles,
slides and hops, amazing
movements of the hips and feet.
That in time, became buck
and wing, juba, turkey trot,
the mooche, tap dance, lindy,
charleston, big apple,
the twist; every day a new
dance, every beat, a new step.
Master Juba added a Jig and
became a world sensation.
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
Sly parodies of plantation
quadrilles
and minuets became the cakewalk.
[ Ruth Brisbane singing "Strut Miss Lizzy" ]
All the dusky
belles were there
They were singin', bringin',
prancin' and a dancin'
They were doing for fair
All the belles and beaus,
prancin' on their toes
try to do the cakewalks well
When a midnight blonde
came prancin' on
and they were heard to yell:
Won't you strut
Miss Lizzy, get busy
I want to see you walk
for the folks all state
the way you syncopate
As the whole town talks,
when you walk so pretty
and it's a pity
the other girlies frown
but the men you meet,
like the way you shake your feet
Oh, you knock them dizzy,
strut Miss Lizzy Brown!
[ Applause ]
[ Jazz Music ]
>> Nineteen hundred
and thirty-two,
we were doing the Big Apple and
Susy Q. We're balling the Jack
and doing the Bebop.
Right now
[ Audience Laughter ]
We're gonna
We're gonna?
We're gonna Lindy Hop!
You all ready for us?!
[ Drum roll ]
[ Music ]
Ho!  Oh yeah!
Alright!
[ Jazz Music, Clapping ]
[ Applause ]
[ Applause, Jazz Music ]
[ Bliss Harmonizers singing: "The Way
You Do the Things You Do" ]
The way you swept
me off my feet
You know you could've
been a broom.
And Baby you're so sweet,
You know you could've
been some perfume.
Well you could've been anything
that you wanted to
and I can tell the way
you do the things you do.
The way you do the thing you do.
You really swept me off my feet.
The way you do the
things you do.
You made my life complete.
The way you do the
things you do.
You made my life so fine.
The way you do the
things you do.
You made me feel alright.
The way you do the
things you do.
Well, you could have
been anything
that you wanted to,
and I can tell
The way you
>> Chuck.
Come on [inaudible].
This is for Chuck.
Chucky baby. Chuck.
You do.
The things that you do.
>> Here you go Chuck.
This is for you Chuck.
do
The way you do
the things you do.
>> Let him get it by himself.
Go ahead Chuck.
[ Laughter ]
[ Clapping ]
[ Background Conversations ]
>> Show on the stage.
There's a show on the
stage, keep it down.
[ Tap Dancing ]
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
>> Ladies and gentlemen,
The Magnificent Force
directed by Julie Fraad.
And the dancers are:
Icey Ice,
Freeze,
Fresh Frank,
Cosmic Pop Force,
Fastbreak,
Kid Rock,
and Easy Ease.
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
[ Harmonica Music ]
>> One, two, three, four.
[ Applause ]
>> One, two, three, go!
>> One, one
>> Two, two
>> Three, three
>> Four, four
>> Five, five
>> Six, six
>> Seven, seven
>> Eight, eight
>> Nine, nine
>> Exit
[ Applause ]
>> Move your feet, Sheri.
>> Come on, stay with me.
>> Come on Sheri, move your feet.
>> Move it, Sheri.
>> You have to turn it.
Come on.
>> You can do it.
[ Applause ]
>> Come on Wanda.
>> Come on Wanda, you can do it.
Stay with us.
Pick it up.
Watch the feet Wanda.
Breathe Wanda!
Pick it up!
Come on!
Come on, pick it up!
Go!
>> Pick up your feet.
Show it!
[ Applause ]
>> One, two, three, go
>> Easy, Jazzy Jumpers!
>> OK, Come on Sheri.
Pick 'em up.
One, two, three, go.
[ Applause ]
Come on you got it.
One, two, three, go.
One, two, three.
Come on, take you time Tina.
>> Take your time Tina.
>> One, two, three,
>> To the North, yeah,
to the South, yeah,
Jazzy Jumpers gonna
turn it out.
To the East, yeah,
to the West, yeah,
Jazzy Jumpers are the best.
>> Take your time.
[ Applause ]
>> One, two, three, go.
One, two, three, go.
One, two, three.
>> Pick it up!
Pick it up!
[ Applause ]
>> We are the Jazzy Jumpers.
>> Get down Tina.
>> Just pick up your feet,
that's all.
>> Switch!
>> One, two, three,
to the North, yeah,
to the South, yeah, Jazzy
Jumpers gonna turn it out.
To the East, yeah,
to the West, yeah,
Jazzy Jumpers are the best.
>> Switch!
Take your time now Tina.
>> Take you time Sheri.
>> Come on.
>> Come on Sheri you can do it.
Pick 'em up.
Come on, pick it up Sheri.
[ Applause ]
>> Come on.
>> One, two,
one, two, three, four.
[ Applause ]
One, two, three.
>> Now that's Double Dutch.
[ Applause ]
>> We'll get on it [inaudible].
>> You all were very good.
>> Thank you.
>> And Wanda keep your feet up.
>> Yeah.
[ Multiple Speakers ]
[ Laughter ]
>> That crazy lady.
Fontessa.
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
Fontessa was a very
eccentric character.
She wasn't a real person.
It's just someone that, that
John named Fontessa I think
because it's just the name just
sort of described the person.
So, I just named the ballet
"Fontessa and Friends"
[ Music ]
[ Crazy Laughing ]
[ Ragtime Music ]
[ Audience Laughter ]
[ Applause ]
[ Ragtime Music ]
[ Wild Laughter ]
[ Ragtime Music, fast tempo ]
[ Applause ]
[ Audience Laughter ]
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
[ Audience Laughter ]
[ Music ]
[ Audience Laughter, Clapping ]
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
[ Audience Laughter ]
[ Audience Cheering ]
[ Music ]
[ Audience Laughter ]
[ Audience Laughter, Clapping ]
[ Music ]
[ Audience Laughter ]
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
[ Audience Laughter ]
[ Cheering ]
[ Music ]
[ Audience Laughter ]
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
[ Audience Laughter ]
[ Muisc ]
[ Music ]
[ Audience Laughter ]
[ Applause ]
>> Shh. Shh.
Shh. Shh. Shhhhhh.
[ Music ]
[ Linda Clifford singing "If My
Friends Could See Me Now" ]
If they could see me now,
that old gang of mine
I'm eating fancy chow
and drinking fancy wine
I'd like those stumble bums
to see for a fact
the kind of top drawer,
first rate chums I attract
All I can say is, Wow!
Hey, look at
where I am
I landed Pow!
Right in a pot of jam
What a setup, holy cow!
? They'd never believe it ?
If my friends could see me
If they could see me
Said if my friends
could see me
If they could see me
Oh, if my friends
could see me
If they could
see me now!
If they could see me
in my Cadillac Seville
If they could see me up in
diamonds all the time
Diamonds, diamonds, diamonds!
If they could see me with
my macho boy of choice
Oh! I'm giving up all my
poverty, now we can all rejoice!
If they could see me now
my little dusty prince
chasing round this
million dollar chick
and hear those real hip cats
say, "Brother, dig her"
draped on a bedspread
made of three kinds of fur!
To think the highest brow
which I must say is me
should pick the lowest brow
which there's no doubt is he
What a step down, holy cow!
They'd never believe it
If my friends could see me
If they could see me
If all my friends
could see me
If they could see me
Said if my friends
could see me
If they could see me
If they could see me now!
in my Cadillac Seville
Hey!
If they could see me up
in diamonds all the time
All the time
If they could see me
with my macho boy of choice
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
[ Music/Applause ]
[ Crazy Laughter ]
[ Applause ]
[ Jazz Music/Clapping ]
[ Music/Clapping ]
[ Music/Applause ]